<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Oxford before the Kings Maiesty, April 19. 1643. VVherein is handled the vnlawfulnesse of non-preaching bishops, non-residents, plurality of benefices, &amp;c. with the utter destruction of images. According to the votes of both the houses of Parliament, scripture, ancient writers, and reason it selfe. By Richard Spinkes, minister of the word of God, and imprisoned there for the said sermon.</title>
            <author>Spinkes, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E104_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E104[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Oxford before the Kings Maiesty, April 19. 1643. VVherein is handled the vnlawfulnesse of non-preaching bishops, non-residents, plurality of benefices, &amp;c. with the utter destruction of images. According to the votes of both the houses of Parliament, scripture, ancient writers, and reason it selfe. By Richard Spinkes, minister of the word of God, and imprisoned there for the said sermon.</title>
                  <author>Spinkes, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the yeare, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 27".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans I, 14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in OXFORD Before the KINGS Maieſty, April 19. 1643.</p>
            <p>VVherein is handled the vnlawfulneſſe of Non-preaching Biſhops, Non-reſidents, plurality of Benefices, &amp;c. with the utter deſtruction of IMAGES.</p>
            <p>According to the votes of both the Houſes of Parliament, Scripture, Ancient Writers, and Reaſon it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Spinkes,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned there for the ſaid Sermon.</p>
            <q>I have preached righteouſneſſe in the great Congregation: loe, I have not refrained my lips, O Lord thou knoweſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 40.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For though I preach the Goſpel, I have nothing to glory of: for neceſsity is laid upon me, yea, woe is unto me, if I preach not the Goſpel, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 9.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>London, printed in the yeare, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:155930:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155930:2"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached before the King in <hi>Oxford,</hi> againſt the Biſhops.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 1.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I am a debtor to the Grecian and Barbarian, to the wiſe and unwiſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe debt which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did owe to theſe Barbarians and Grecians was to preach the word of God, the Goſpel of Chriſt unto them, for ſo it is found added in ſome of the Syriacke copies tranſlated by <hi>Tremellius,</hi> where followeth theſe words, at the later end of the verſe, <hi>I am a debtor to every man to preach unto him.</hi> And ſo <hi>Lyranus</hi> gloſſeth it, <hi>Debitor ſum ad praedicandum Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ex officio Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtolatus,</hi> As I am an Apoſtle it is my <hi>debitum,</hi> my due to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt. The labour of the Apoſtle was not limited to any private Church or Nation, but whereſoever a doore of utterance, an occaſion of good did offer it ſelfe, they were to apprehend the opportunity. Their commiſſion is large, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Goe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and teach all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> This they were bound to doe upon a great forfeiture, the invaluable loſſe of their owne ſoules, upon paine of Gods heavie diſpleaſure, and everlaſting perdition, for ſo much doth the word <hi>vae</hi> every where imply in the Scripture, ſaith Saint <hi>Jerome.</hi> Though I preach the Goſpel, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. yet have I nothing to glory of, for a neceſſity is laid upon me, and woe be unto me if I preach not the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The parties which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth himſelfe to be indebted unto, or rather Gods aſſignees (for hee is the principall in the bond) are Grecians and Barbarians, and all the Gentiles; for though ſome would have the Jewes to be included in the word <hi>wiſe,</hi> as they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a forme of knowledge and wiſedome in the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20. yet I take the Gentiles to have beene more properly of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, they are both named I confeſſe in the commiſſion, but the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles firſt: <hi>Hee is a choſen veſſell unto me to beare my name before the
<pb facs="tcp:155930:3"/>Gentiles, and Kings, and the children of Iſrael, Acts</hi> 9.15. In this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle he is called the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, becauſe unto him is ſud (by a private compact among the Apoſtles) to have beene committed the Goſpel of uncircumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.7. and againe <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Vnto me who am l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe then the leaſt of all the Saints is this grace given that I ſhould preach among the Gentiles the unſearchable riches of Chriſt:</hi> this was the ſtocke he was truſted with, the debts which he oweth them.</p>
            <p>Now whereas all Miniſters are ſucceſſors to the Apoſtles, though not <hi>quoad gradum &amp; modum miniſterii: (id eſt)</hi> not according to the degree and manner of their calling, yet <hi>quoad eſſentiam doctrinae, (id eſt)</hi> according to the ſubſtance of the errand: and ſeeing that the preferring of certaine men to ſeverall congregations is of divine inſtitution, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Feed the flocke of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof.</hi> I may warrant this obſervation.</p>
            <p>That all Miniſters or Paſtors are indebted, are bound in conſcience to preach the word of God to the charge they have undertaken. A ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject I confeſſe of as dangerous and untractable an argument as any whatſoever, from diſcuſsing of which I might be deterred with thoſe motives wherewith the Prieſt in <hi>Ariſt.</hi> Rhetorick dehorted his ſon from being an Orator; for ſaid he, If thou ſpeak that which is juſt men will hate thee: if that which is unjuſt the gods will abhor thee.</p>
            <p>This incompetition betweene God and man was enough to put a Heathen to a great ſtrait, all whoſe happineſſe, and the reward of all whoſe actions conſiſted in the good report and opinion of them, but a Chriſtian will ſoone reſolve it, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19. <hi>VVhether it be better to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God or men, judge ye. Gal.</hi> 1.10. <hi>For if I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi> It is ſaid of our Saviour by the Spouſe in the Canticles, that his lips drop all myrrhe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>Truth like this may be bitter, yet it is wholeſome doctrine: what therefore our Saviour ſaid to <hi>Martha</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.41. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha thou art carefull about many things, but one thing is neceſſary,</hi> might well be objected to a generall action of men in theſe dayes, who as S. <hi>Panl</hi> ſaid of <hi>James John,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> ſeeme to be pillars to beare up a great burthen in the Church, and to take a great deale of paines, but upon proofe it will appeare that it is nothing but a cold ſweat, or a pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant humour, rather then the ſymptome of any true zeale. They have perhaps two Churches abroad, yet are ſo buſie about reforming one Chappell at home, that ſhould the Lord ſay to them in a Colledge as
<pb facs="tcp:155930:3"/>be did once to <hi>Eliah</hi> in the cave, a <hi>King.</hi> 19.9. they would anſwer (I make no queſtion) in the words of the Prophet, <hi>VVe have beene very realous for the Lord of hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is a true ſaying of <hi>Maximus, Tyrius</hi> the Philoſopher, A good and religious man is Gods friend, but a ſuperſtitious fellow is Gods flatterer, for with his mouth he ſhewes much love, and flitters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his owne eyes; untill his iniquity be found out to be hatefull <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.1. The two Table, Gods Commandements are the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone or try all of our love: <hi>Ye are my friends</hi> (faith Chriſt) <hi>if yee doe whatſoever I command you, Iohn</hi> 15.14. Now our bleſſed Saviour hath urged this Commandement not leſſe then thrice, <hi>Peter, loveſt thou me, feed my ſheepe;</hi> As thou loveſt me <hi>Peter,</hi> feed my Lambs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Nicene Conncell that met together for the eſtabliſhing of Idolatry, and admitting Images into Churches, being hard beſtead for arguments, were not aſhamed to make uſe of that place in the Pſalmes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8. <hi>I have loved the habitation of thy houſe, and the place where thy honour dwelloth: but the enemies of the Lord ſhall bee found to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ars.</hi> God himſelfe ſaith expreſly, that all ſuch hate him, in the ſecond Commandement, <hi>Though alt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image, to bow downe unto it, &amp;c. for I am a jealous God, and viſit the finnes of the Fathers upon the children, unto the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of thoſe that hate me.</hi> The beauty of Gods houſe, as <hi>Caſſidore</hi> well obſerveth in the expoſition of that very Pſalme, conſiſts not <hi>in pulchrnudine parictum, ant Ministrorum pret to ſiſſimo apparatu, (id eſt)</hi> not in painting and pargetting of the wall with Moſaick works, not in anticking the windowes with Legends, not in coping the Miniſters in ſumptuous and gorgeous apparell, but in the humble and fervent devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prayer, the ſincere and powerfull preaching of Gods word; the only image that ought to be in every Church, is the Miniſter, who if he be painfull and religious, is as (<hi>lomens Alexandriuus, Strom. lib.</hi> 5. calleth him, A living image of God by whoſe exemplary carriage the people ſhould learne to frame and faſhion their lives. For ſuch a one whiles others are mechanically ſtriving to convert Tables of wood into Altars of ſtone, doth by the bleſsing of God upon his labours, and by the ſacred Chymiſtry of the holy Ghoſt, convert ſtones into gold; for a broken heart (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſost. Hom.</hi> 4. <hi>in Mat.</hi>) is <hi>Aureum altare,</hi> a golden Altar. How God is preſent at others Altars, let them diſpute that worſhip them, but ſure I am that the Lord is nigh unto
<pb facs="tcp:155930:4"/>them that are of a broken, and will ſave ſuch as are of a contrite ſpirit. <hi>I would they were cut off that trouble you,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul. Gal.</hi> 5.12. The truth is there might well be ſpared a great number among us, who like fruitleſſe trees doe but cumber the ground, and fraudulently attract the nouriſhment which would ſufficiently releeve and maintain many others: but it were rather to be wiſhed that thoſe trifles about which they beat their fellow ſervants, were utterly aboliſhed. Upon the Reformation of Religion in Helvetia, <hi>Anno</hi> 1528. They of Baſil pulling downe all their Images out of their Churches brought them into their publique market place, there to be divided for fuell among the poore people, but when they fell a fighting and brawling about the ſharing of them, it was at laſt generally agreed by the Counſell of the City, to make one faire fire of them publiquely, and to burne them all together, which day being Aſh-wedneſday is yet in the memory of that act celebrated with many paſtimes and ſolemnities.</p>
            <p>So were it a happy thing for this Church and Commonwealth if all thoſe Reliques of ſuperſtition were burnt together, rather then ſuch combuſtions, ſuch heart-burnings, ſhould be fomented and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among us, and that all would joyntly ſet themſelves to the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, which is that <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> many matters of leſſe importance called for with a great deale of more rigour, are but things of veniall indifferency, but this is of an abſolute and undiſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table neceſſity every Prieſt, every Miniſter is indebted, is bound in conſcience to diſcharge this duty. I am to prove it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Firſt they are bound by the calling which they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, <hi>Let every man wherein he was called therein abide with God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. Every man ought to have ſome calling or other, whereby he may be ſerviceable to God, or uſefull to his neighbour. God and man, ſaith <hi>Heſido:</hi> who have nothing to doe, who idle drone away all their dayes.</p>
            <p>It is well obſerved by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that in all the day workes of the Creation, the Creator is onely ſtiled God, <hi>God ſaid, Let there be light,</hi> and <hi>God ſaid, Let the earth bring forth graſſe:</hi> but he never uſed the name of Lord till man was framed, and then it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The Lord God planted a garden Eaſtward in Eden:</hi> and ſo ten times in that Chapter: but in the very beginning of the next Chapter, the Divell being to ſeduce the woman, and through his ſubtilty to worke the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mankind, leave, that out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. <hi>Yea hath God ſaid Ye ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:155930:4"/>not eat, &amp;c.</hi> But God in the deſpite of him and all his inſtruments, is the onely Lord of all mankinde, his Lawes doe alone binde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, If he ſay to one Goe, he muſt goe, if to another, Come, hee muſt come; there muſt be no pretending of Statutes and Diſpenſations from Popes and Princes: It is ſaid to all Chriſtians; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Yee are bought with a price, be ye not the ſervants of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all men Miniſters are by ſpeciall relation and dependancy the ſervants of God: ſo they are termed by the holy Ghoſt, 3 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.24. The ſervants of the Lord, (that is, the Miniſters) muſt not ſtrive. And in the Parable of the Talents, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.14. it is ſaid that the Lord called unto him his owne ſervants: and therefore if they looke for any wages, they muſt doe his worke, they need not be aſhamed of it, it is the ſame which their Lord and Maſter was ſent to doe and was imployed about; of whom the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold, <hi>Iſa</hi> 61.1. and our Saviour it to himſelfe, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel. As my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent me, even ſo ſend I you,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt otherwhere) What was his meaning Saint <hi>Paul</hi> plainly telleth us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.37, <hi>God ſent mee not to baptize but to preach;</hi> that was the maine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of their vocation and this was the employment and practice of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Primitive Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Martyrs, who ſealed the doctrine they painfully taught, with their owne bloud. <hi>Prodig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i inſtar erat,</hi> as ſaith <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpencaeus,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ny hundred yeares after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hee was counted a very prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gy of Chriſtianity who tooke upon him the name of a Biſhop and was not a conſtant and an aſſiduous Preacher. And to this day in the forme of conſecration of Biſhops over Sea is the clauſe uſed (I know not how well obſerved) <hi>Vade, &amp; praedica Evangelium populo tibi commiſſo:</hi> Goe and preach the Goſpel to the people committed to thy charge. And in our preſent forme of Ordination of all Miniſters, the Biſhop askes the party to be ordained, Will ye faithfully inſtruct and teach the people committed to thy charge? he anſwers, I will, God being my helpe: which I take to be an oath, and as much as, God ſhall helpe me. And therefore I cannot perceive how they who have forgotten that promiſe, can ſatisfie their conſcience in caſe of perjury, unleſſe God himſelfe hath diſabled them by ſome corporall infirmity. Neither have ſome upon the ſame reaſon thought it lawfull for thoſe who have taken upon this profeſſion, to intermeddle with ſecular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>crity or to execute any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:155930:5"/>teth the opinion of ſome ancient Divine to this purpoſe, To conferre a place of civill government, or outward policy upon a Prieſt, were to reconcile things in their owne nature incompetible to joyne thoſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether whom God himſelfe hath put aſunder: when ſome in the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> provided that as the beſt meanes to provide for the reſidency of Prelates to prohibit them the Courts of Princes, and to forbid them to undertake any civill Office, or to be Judges, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Councellors, Secretaries of State, or the like, which thoſe muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous humoriſts (as they call them) urged to be expreſſy forbid out of the word of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. A good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt ought not to intangle himſelfe with the affaires of this life. The Biſhop of the five Churches, for ſo was his title, being their Ambaſſadour for the Emperour oppoſed that, ſaying. That if Prelates were forbid to wait upon Princes (as they were admitted at that preſent into the Courts of the greateſt Princes and Prelates of Chriſtendome, and there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged the great affaires of State) it would bring the Church into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: and if Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and lay officers were made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible, none of the Nobility would ever after ſo much releeve their blond and diſcent, as to accept of orders. This was a reaſon of State, rather then of religion and conſcience. Had Saint <hi>Paul</hi> been of their counſell, but alas the poore man had he appeared in the threed bare cloake which he left at <hi>Troas,</hi> in the midſt of ſuch an Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an conventicle of mitred and ſcarſeted Prelates, he would have beene of as ominous a preſence as the Owle at the opening at Conſtance, he would have beene of the ſame minde that he was, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17. <hi>Let us that are of the ministery wait on our ministery, and he that teacheth on teaching;</hi> he would never have given his counſell that thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt themſelves of this calling, ſhould leave the word of God to ſerve Tables. I doe not know how ſit ſuch undertakers are for an earthly kingdome, but that flouriſhing Ariſtocracy of the Venetians, out of juſt diſlike have excluded the Clergy out of their conſultations, for when they goe about to adviſe of matters of moment and ſecreſie, the <hi>Praeco</hi> ſtands up and cryes, Let all Prieſts depart the roome: how ever I am ſure that of the Goſpel is true, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62. <hi>No man having put his hand to the plough, and looking backe, is fit for the kingdome of heaven.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us of ſome that worke not at all, and yet are buſie bodies, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.11. There is no greater idleneſſe then to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe. <hi>Minister dix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, hoc age;</hi> Preaching is the high
<pb facs="tcp:155930:5"/>worke, the prop and maine worke of that high calling, which that worthy and painfull Biſhop Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> was ſo well affected too, as that he was wont to wiſh that he might be ſurpriſed by his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the very act. <hi>Tanta fuit illa ſermonis ſacra cupido,</hi> as <hi>Pontius</hi> in his life relates of him, <hi>ut optaret, ſic ſibi paſsionis vota contingere, ut dum de Deo loqueretur in ipſo ſermonis opere necaretur:</hi> That when he was in the Pulpit his ſoule ſhould make him like the chariot of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab,</hi> that if the malice of his enemies would give him that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable interring, the Pulpit might be made his coffin, and the Church his Monument, Let others ſtudy to gaine the name of Politicians, ſuch as he was are the moſt faithful and wiſeſt ſervants that God hath. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.25.26. <hi>VVho then is a faithfull and wiſe ſervant, whom his Lord hath made ruler over his houſhould, to give them meat in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, bleſſed is that ſervant whom his Lord when he commeth ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> They are in debted and bound in conſcience to this duty, by reaſon of the gifts and graces which God hath beſtowed upon them for the diſcharge of this ſervice, God never intended any for this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but he firſt furniſhed them with gifts and abilities for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable execution thereof. So the Apoſtles and Diſciples were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to depart from Jeruſalem till the promiſe of the Father, the gift of the holy Ghoſt was poured upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4. They indeed were miraculouſly and at an inſtant inſtructed by the Spirit of God, and it is ſtill the ſame Father of lights that enlightens every one that commeth into the world, from whom comes every good and perfect gift, who gives a bleſſing to our ſtudious endeavours.</p>
            <p>For the Church can neither conferre gifts neceſſary to the miniſtry, nor preſcribe God the parties upon whom he ſhould beſtow them, but are oneſy to rake notice of, and chooſe thoſe whom upon tryall and experience of their gifts they perceive the Lord hath fitted, according to the rule of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Let them first be examined, and then admit them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In juſtice none ought to be admitted to the Miniſtery, unleſſe they bring Gods <hi>Conge de eſtire</hi> with them, unleſſe they be enriced by him in all utterance and in all knowledge, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15. Now theſe gifts are not in propriety our owne they are called his ſubſtance, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.14. we are but <hi>uſufructuaries</hi> to improve our talents to the uſe and intereſt of our Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155930:6"/>
            <p>All thoſe therefore upon whom God hath conferred ſuch gifts, doe become indebted to the people of God, eſpecially to their paſtorall charge over which the holy Ghoſt hath made them overſeers: for God giveth us them not to pleaſe our ſelves in the conceit of them, but to employ them to the benefit and edification of his Church, that Church with which we are betruſted, whether <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> all are yours, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>I am</hi> (ſaid the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.25.) <hi>made a Miniſter according to the gift of God which is given to me for you to fulfill the word of God. As every man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift</hi> (ſaith Saith <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.) <hi>even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold graces of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſhew you plainly that it is a due debt, the Lord hath given the people a Letter of Attorney to call for the ſame, and demand it, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. whence he bids the people ſay to <hi>Archippus, Take heed to thy miniſtery which thou haſt received of the Lord, that thou fulfill it:</hi> that is, that thou preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, <hi>importune &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune.</hi> For what the Scripture ſaith of that union and myſtery of marriage, that the body of the husband is not his owne, but his wives, is true of the ſpirituall tye and conjunction betweene a Miniſter and his charge, his body, his health, his ſtrength, are not his owne, but the Churches: as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> writ to <hi>Dracontius</hi> the Monke, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſe to a Biſhopricke, for ſome inconvemences of ayre or ſicua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion perhaps refuſed it, <hi>Non ſibi amplius, ſed Eccleſiae utilitati ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endums eſſe,</hi> you muſt no longer ſaid that holy and religious Patriarch, ſerve your ſelfe, ſeeke your owne eaſe and advancement, but the profit and welfare of Gods Church. I cannot perceive but the City of Corinth was by reaſon of the proximity of two Seas ſituate in as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and obnoxious an ayre, as any whatſoever: yet this holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, though he was called from them, and diſtracted with the cares of other Churches, yet he was never Nonreſident in heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, though the more I love you the leſſe I am beloved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a great deale of prodigality in the Greeke, it is as our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme</hi> expounds it, <hi>Vit on meam, fotritus meos, fanguinem meum effun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp; exhauriam pro vobis:</hi> I would very gladly ſhed my bloud, lay downe my life, ſpend my ſpirits to doe you good I count nothing too deare or thoſe whom Chriſt h th purchaſed with his owne bloud, as he other where expreſſeth himſelfe to the Theſſalonian, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:155930:6"/>affectionately deſirous, we were willing to have inaparted unto you not the Goſpel of God onely, but alſo our owne ſelves, becauſe ye were deare unto us. If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and his painfull aſſiſtants did through the love of God ſhed abroad in their hearts, ſo highly prize thoſe to whom they were ſtrangers by country and alliance, as to give their ſoules for them.</p>
            <p>They have but ſmall love to Chriſt, what ever they talke of it, who will not adventure their bodies, nor indanger their healths for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life of thoſe to whom they have a neere relation.</p>
            <p>It was a wicked and ungracious ſpeech of thoſe in the Pſalmes, <hi>Our lips are our owne, who is Lord over us?</hi> Miniſters muſt know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they have a Lord to whom they muſt one day be accomptable and their tongues are not their owne, for, <hi>The Prteſts lips ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledge, and the people ſhould ſeeke the law at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of hoſts, Math.</hi> 2.7. He that hid his talent in the ground, had as good have ſtolne it: The Lord doth not onely call him idle, but alſo wicked ſervant: Idleneſſe is the tutor of all vice and wickedneſſe. <hi>Sozomen. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. reporteth of <hi>Amonius</hi> the Monke, that to avoid a Biſhopricke (for ſuch dignities bring them places of burden and charge were not ſo highly prized, ſo eagerly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and ſought for, as of latter times, but were glad to goe a begging for able and ſufficient men) cut off his eare, (for ſuch was the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of that minority of the Church, that a corporall blemiſh and deformity made a man uncapable of that promotion.) Not long after <hi>Evagrius</hi> a man of knowne parts and ſufficiency, but emulating the glory of that action, was choſen and preferred by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Biſhop of Alexandria to the like dignity, did likewiſe withdraw himſelfe into the wilderneſſe, till the votes of the people were devolved upon ſome other.</p>
            <p>It fortuned after that he met with <hi>Amouius,</hi> and told him that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had made a faire eſeape, whereas he by cutting off his eare had beene injurious to his owne body, and had by violent hands incurred the guilt of ſelfe-maiming. To this <hi>Amouius</hi> modeſtly replyed, <hi>At tu non put as te poenas datur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m quod lingua propter nimium tui ipſius ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem exciſa gratia, qua à Deo tibi donata est, mimmè viſus?</hi> Doſt thou thinke to eſcape the judgement of God, who through too much ſelfe love haſt voluntarily cut out thy tongue in not uſing that grace which God hath given thee, to the edification of his Church. No doubtleſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:155930:7"/>for this very end doth God furniſh us with knowledge and utterance that we ſhould impart the truth unto others, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 50.4. <hi>The Lord God hath given me the tongue of the learned, that I ſhould know how to ſpeake a word inſeaſon to him that is weary. Achan</hi> the theeſe was ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſtealing from Jericho a wedge of gold. It is in the Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which properly ſignifieth as it is in the margent, a tongue of gold: their ſacriledge (beleeve it) is not leſſe puniſhable, who rob the people of God of the inſtruction that is due unto them, the wants of which tend to their utter deſtruction, and impoveriſhing of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Faith is much more precions then gold which periſheth, ſaith Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. <hi>But how ſhould they beleeve without a Preacher?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10.14. There is gold, and a company of Rubies (ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 20.15.) but the lips of knowledge are a pretious jewel, and he that wrongs the owner of them, it is as much as his ſoule is worth. And therefore I am perſwaded that thoſe who firſt ſeized upon the temporals of the Church, were not guilty of ſo much ſacriledge as in enacting that Statute whereby Miniſters are authoriſed to diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue from their livings till forty yeares of age, had it beene thirty yeares there might have beene ſome ſeeming exenſe and warrant from the example of Chriſt, who did not take upon him the Miniſtery until he was, as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.23. about thirty yeares of age: and ſo <hi>Gregory Nazianz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> would have none to undertake this calling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be arived to a perfect age and ſtatute, alluding I ſuppoſe to the age of our Saviour, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>a perfect man Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. and his age, <hi>the meaſure of ſtature;</hi> and much about the ſame age was Saint <hi>Paul</hi> called or God to the Miniſtery, for he lived 68 yeares, of which he ſpent 35. in preaching the Goſpel, as <hi>Baronius</hi> reports out of <hi>Chryſostome:</hi> but 40. yeares is the rerme of impenitency which ſeems in Scripture to put the Lord himſelfe, who is long ſuffering and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, out of patience with wicked and ungodly men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.10. <hi>Forty yeares long have I beene grieved with this generation, &amp;c. wherefore I ſware in my wrath that they ſhould not enter into my reſt.</hi> Some there are who though they be opimerate that they would ſcorne to come into competition for learning with many of their induſtrious neighbours in the Country, pretend they doe diſcontinue from their charges, and live in ſome Schoole of the Prophets, thereby to better their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and to gaine a great meaſure of knowledge, by hearing of
<pb facs="tcp:155930:7"/>Acts and controverſies ſcholaſtically handled: but what <hi>Eliab, Davids</hi> elde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brother ſaid to him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28. <hi>VVith whom haſt thou left thoſe few ſheeps in the wilderneſſe? I know the pride and haughtineſſe of thy heart, thou art come forth to ſee the battell:</hi> may (I feare) be ſaid too truly of a number of ſuch who care not with whom they leave the ſoules committed to their charge and cuſtody, that they ſtudy rather their owne promotion then the good of the Church, another Benefice rather then to benefit their underſtanding.</p>
            <p>He that is to be ordained Miniſter ought to be for the preſent 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>apt to teach,</hi> fit to teach: that is (as <hi>Catharmus</hi> a learned Biſhop doth paraphraſe on the words) he muſt be one <hi>qui ſciat docere &amp; non indigeat deſcere, ſed qui actu doceat plebeculam ſuam,</hi> one who further is able to inſtruct the flocke committed to him, and need not ſtill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be taught, let ſuch conſider what our Saviour ſaith to his ſervants to whom he gave the Talents in the goſpel, he doth not ſay (as <hi>Stella</hi> obſerves upon <hi>Luke</hi>) <hi>Diſcite dum venio, ſed negotiamim dum venio,</hi> Traffique and imploy till I come. For what is Divinity which we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſtudy? Is it not a ſcience onely of diſputing acutely and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly of every point of controverſie, as a reverend Profeſſor of ours, <hi>Bako:</hi> in his firſt Lecture upon <hi>Jonas</hi> confeſſeth:} but it conſuts rather <hi>In bona conſcientia, quam in bona ſcientia;</hi> in a good then in abundance of knowledge and ſcience. And the beſt way to increaſe their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is to be faithfull in a little, to imploy that little that they have to the benefit of others, in the conſcionable diſcharge of their calling, according to the golden rule of our Saviour, <hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 7.17. <hi>If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny man will doe his will be ſhall know his doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> Diligence of Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is commended by the Spirit of God, though at firſt he knew not ſo much as his fellowes, yet by the preaching of his gifts he much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25.26. This man being fervent in ſpirit, ſpake and taught diligently the things of the Lord, knowing onely the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of <hi>John:</hi> but in the next verſe he met with ſome hearers, who raught him the word of God more perfectly: for it is not with this as with other debts (ſaith Chriſt) for abroad the debtors ſhun the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and are loath to come within his reach. But I follow you and intreat you to receive that which I owe you, inſtruction; and that not without reaſon, for they if they pay their debts have the leſſe, ſeeme to be the poorer for it, but when I pay you and diſcharge this debt of my calling I am the richer for it, for what is my hope, my joy
<pb facs="tcp:155930:8"/>my crowne of rejoycing, <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Are not even ye in the preſence of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt at his comming?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, let ſuch remember how that ſervant that hid his Talent in the earth, was doom'd and ſentenced in the Goſpel, <hi>Take and caſt that unprofitable ſervant into utter darkneſſe.</hi> Hee doth not ſay that debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, wicked, filthy, malicious, proud, drunken and prophane villaine, but it was enough to damne him that he did no good, <hi>caſt out that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Thirdly, Miniſters are bound in conſcience to preach to their charges, by reaſon of the danger which by their ſilence and neglect will aſſuredly redound to the ſoules committed to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> was the queſtion of the firſt murtherer: Miniſters muſt make no queſtion of it; the holy Ghoſt hath ſo plainly and peremptorily affirmed it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you;</hi> the Greeke may well be interpreted <hi>Priests, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſoules as thoſe that muſt give an account for them.</hi> I diſpute not here about the infallibility of Gods predeſtination, the foundation of God ſtands ſure, and he knowes who are his: but if thou doſt not build upon that foundation, if thou doeſt not by all meanes endeavour to reclaime the moſt deſperate and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible ſinner, his bloud ſhall be laid to thy charge: <hi>Non pavaſts, occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti,</hi> that Miniſter that is not a paſtor is a murtherer, ſaith Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe:</hi> for when the viſion failes, the people muſt needs periſh, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. And ſo the Lord telleth us of a ſort of Prophets, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.19. that for a handfull of Barley and a piece of bread (that is) for baſe and ſiniſter reſpects did ſlay the ſoules of thoſe that ſhould not dye, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the truth of God from them. The Lawyers ſay well, <hi>qas cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam damni dat ipſum damnum dediſſe videtur.</hi> It is as true of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God will eaſily acquit his Juſtice againſt the moſt ſlanderous and blaſphemous imputations, when thouſands of the damned ſhall bitterly curſe the idleneſſe of their Miniſters, which was the cauſe of their ignorance. <hi>Sonne of man,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.20. <hi>I have made thee a watchman, if thou deſt not warne the wicked to returne from his wicked way, he ſhall die, but his bloud will I require at thy hand.</hi> Hee whom the King ſhould employ to carry a pardon to a company of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, that every moment are in danger of execution, ſhould bee drinke himſelfe drunke by the way, or be detained by every triviall occaſion, were a great deale more cruell then the hangman. So the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb facs="tcp:155930:8"/>who are, as the Prophet calls them, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. the meſſengers of the Lord of hoſts, and hath a pardon in his boſome, the Goſpell of peace, by preaching and publiſhing of which he might both ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and thoſe that heare him. If he beginnes to eate and drinke and to be drunken, <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.41. if hee doe not goe about the errand that God hath ſent him (who would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth) but be detained by the way by every ſhift and pretence, is for all the Lawes and Statutes that can bee pretended a moſt impardonable murtherer. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who here confeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a debtor, had not he diſcharged his duty, and got a <hi>quietus est</hi> on record to his conſcience, other where by the ſame Logicke of the holy Ghoſt had concluded himſelfe a murtherer: <hi>Acts</hi> 20.26. <hi>I take you to record this day, that I am pure from the bloud of all men, for I have not ſhunned to declare unto you the whole counſell of God:</hi> but how? by Epiſtle perhaps, or by ſending ſome ſubſtitute to them, as <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Trophimus,</hi> no ſaith he, <hi>but remember how that from houſe to houſe, night and day I intreated every man with teares that he would be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of this duty and dangerous neglect of the ſame, put the holy and induſtrious Biſhop Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> into the ſame extaſie with the Diſciples in the Goſpel, <hi>Lord who then can be ſaved?</hi> I wonder (ſaith he) if it be poſſible that ever any Miniſter or Biſhop ſhould be ſaved. And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> further, <hi>Si pro ſe quiſque, &amp;c.</hi> Good God (ſaith he) if it ſhould bee ſo dangerous a tryall for every man to give an account for his owne ſoule, and that the righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved, <hi>quid fiet de Sacerdotibus?</hi> what ſhall become of me and the Prieſts? that ſtand chargeable and accountable for all the ſoules committed to our overſight. Surely they be not thorowly perſwaded of the danger who ſleepe upon both eares (as they ſay) and purpoſe to give up their accounts by a Proxie. But truly me thinkes ſhould I hold my peace, that loud Oratory of bloud ſhould be enough to awaken the wretchleſſe ſecurity of theſe times, unto a ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. <hi>Scarlet</hi> it ſelfe which is uſually made the cloake of <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidency.</hi> ſhould be but a melancholy ſight and ſad repreſentation to any that hath but the affection of a father; it lookes ſo like <hi>Joſephs</hi> coat as if it were dipt in the bloud of thoſe whom ſome evill beaſt had devoured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cedrinus</hi> reports of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour, that having a jealous eye over the acts of his brother <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> he forced him into Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall
<pb facs="tcp:155930:9"/>Orders, and got him made a Deacon, and from his hand was wont to receive the Cup in the Euchariſt. But at laſt fearing that his worth and deſerts might make ſome faction and party in the Empire, he cauſed him preſently to be put to death, whereupon hee was ever haunted and dogged with the Faries of a clamorous and accuſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and ſo broken and diſquieted in his ſleepe, that oftentimes he ſeemed to ſee his brother comming to him in the habit of a Deacon, preſenting him a cup full of bloud, and ſaying theſe words. <hi>Bibe frater,</hi> Drinke brother.</p>
            <p>And tell me thou that ſtandeſt here idle in the market-place, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending thou art trading for learning and knowledge, thorough thy knowledge ſhall thy poore brother periſh for whom Chriſt died? and ſhall not that imagination of <hi>David</hi> wormwood all thy cups, when thou art drinking the Annuities of thy Livings? is not this the ſweat, is not this the bloud of thoſe men? <hi>Bibe frater,</hi> drinke brother, but know <hi>for all theſe things God will call thee to judgement.</hi> In the hand of the Lord there is a cup too the dregs thereof ſhall all the wicked in the earth drinke. That place of the Goſpel would be better conſidered of a many, <hi>Marke</hi> 6.4. <hi>VVhen our Saviour came out and ſaw much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he was moved with compaſsion towards them, becauſe they were as ſheepe not having a ſhepheard and hee began to teach them many things.</hi> He had compaſſion on them: the word in the Originall is very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall, and is uſed by Saint Matthew upon the ſame occaſion. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.36. <hi>He had compaſsion on them. Commiſeratione ab intimis viſceribus profectum,</hi> ſo <hi>Beza</hi> renders it, his bowels yerned within him, it made his heart bleed to ſee ſo ſad and rufull a ſpectacle. He that hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be with us to the end, doubtleſſe ſeeth us, and therefore will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly one day make their hearts ake, whoſe idleneſſe and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath beene the cauſe of ſo great want as there is in many places, where the maintenance is large enough. That great Shepheard of the flockes (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> cals him) will have a day of viſitation too, in which howſoever now Conformiſts ſpeed, it will be a fearfull one for Non reſidents, elſe that of the Prophet is not true, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord to the Pastors of Iſrael, becauſe you have not viſited my flocke, therefore will I viſit upon you the evill of your doings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> They are bound in conſcience by reaſon of the <hi>Stipend</hi> and meanes which they receive for their Cure, as they improperly call them. Be not angry and I will ſpeak but this once. If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath
<pb facs="tcp:155930:9"/>confeſſed himſelfe a debtor to all Grecians and Barbarians, though no Church communicated with him as concerning giving, but the Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians onely, <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.15. Surely then thoſe Miniſters are much more indebted to their ſeverall Congregations from whom they receive yearly ſuch large Penſions and Annuities. It was the old rule of the Church, <hi>Beneficium datur propter officium,</hi> he that will not do the Lords worke, cannot with a ſafe conſcience eate <hi>punem Dominicam,</hi> demand his penny at night; for he that would not worke ſhould not eate. Every idle man is a theefe, ſaith <hi>Phocilides.</hi> And ſo our Saviour the truth it ſelfe is bold to call all thoſe that are not good and painfull Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.1. that is, as <hi>Muſculus</hi> interprets it, goodneſſe, doe not communicate their grace and knowledge to others, theeves and robbers: And therefore at the great Aſſizes and day of Judgement, when all others are condemned and caſt out of heaven, let not ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Miniſters looke to have the benefit of their Clergie: will hee reſpect your perſons, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.9. all their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that Miniſters have for that their maintenance by the Morall Law of God (the equity of which is perpetuall) is deducted out of that Commandement in the ſecond Table, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> by our Saviours owne gloſſe doth not onely conſiſt in a titular or ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious reverence, but in reall expreſſions of maintenance. So that <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4. commands children to requite their parents: the word in the Syriacke properly ſignifieth Uſe, <hi>Foenus rependant progenitoribus ſuis,</hi> Let them pay uſe to their parents; uſe (I ſuppoſe) for the charge they had beene at in their education and breeding: for <hi>Solon</hi> the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>(Plutar. in Solon)</hi> obſerving how earneſtly ſome men brought up their children, to the great danger and endamaging of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, enacted this Law, That no ſonne ſhould be forced by Law to maintaine that father in his age, who had not taught him or brought him up in ſome Science or Trade, whereby he might get his owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. By what law and conſcience then may many Miniſters demand and exact ſuch large allowance of their Pariſhioners to whom they ſhew themſelves Fathers in nothing, unleſſe it bee by diſinheriting them. <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus I have begotten you through the Goſpel</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. Miniſters can be fathers in no other reſpects to them to whom they are ſet over, but in teaching and inſtructing them in the word of God.</p>
            <p>The Table of the Shew-bread was ſet in the midſt of the Temple,
<pb facs="tcp:155930:10"/>to ſignifie (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi>) quod Sacerdores in Templo ſervientes; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Templo victum habere de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that is, That theſe Prieſts that wait un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the altar ſhould have benefit by it, and none elſe. That is a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable place, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.28. God there commands the Iſraelites whiles they were yet upon their journey to the promiſed Land, that when they came there they ſhould give the Lord Heave-offerings to <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, now <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt died in the wilderneſſe, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, as it is in the next Chapter, which hath cauſed many Cabaliſticall conjecture among the Jewiſh Doctors but their beſt Expoſitors of Scripture, the followers and adherents of Rab: <hi>Iſmael</hi> doe thus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it, That the Lords portion was onely to be given to him amongſt the Prieſts who were skilfull and diligent in the teaching and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Law as was <hi>Aaron,</hi> the reverſion of his maintenance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather intayled upon his worth and deſerts, then to bee chalenged by the hereditary diſcent of any Loyterer, which opinion ſeemes to be countenanced with the authority of that place, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4. When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> commands the people to give the portion to the Prieſts and Levite, that they might be incouraged in the Law of the Lord, not to encourage their idleneſſe: and that Apophthegme of <hi>Rabbi Raccha</hi> in the Talmud is very famous among the Jewes, that he who gives ought to an ignorant, idle, prophane and ungodly Prieſt, doth a worſe deed then if he ſhould caſt it to a Dog, or to a Lyon for theſe creatures may be bettered by ſuch almes; they are of Gods family, and he provides for them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.21. But if a Prieſt who is unworthy, eate of the offerings, it is his poyſon and thou (ſaid he) art acceſſory to his death, by giving it to him. All which he would prove by that place of <hi>Levit.</hi> 22.9, 10. <hi>The Prieſts ſhall keepe my ordinances, lest they beare ſinne for it, and die if they prophane it, if the Lord doe ſanctifie it, Deut.</hi> 23.8.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded verily that that God who would not have the price of a dog to be brought into his Sanctuary, did never intend, and would never give conſent that the Revenues of the Sanctuary, the childrens bread ſhould be given unto dogs. So not I, but he that will juſtifie it, calls idle and ſilent Miniſters, <hi>Iſay</hi> 58.10. <hi>His watchmen are blinde, they are all dumbe dogs, they are all ignorant, they cannot barke, ſleeping, lying downe and loving to ſlumber: they are all Shepheards which cannot underſtand:</hi> they all looke to his owne way, every man to his gaine from the quarter: that is, they will be ſure to demand their annuities, their quarterages; and how doe they ſpend it? merrily in the next
<pb facs="tcp:155930:10"/>verſe, <hi>Come, ſay they, and we will fetch wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drinke, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant.</hi> And here is the true property of dogs indeed, to returne to their vomit, drinke and to it againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> that great Secretary of Nature, acquaints us with a great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of State uſed in that title but exemplary Common-wealth of Bees, thoſe that are Drones, and are by the loſſe of their ſtings become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and unſerviceable to the State are not onely denyed main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, but caſt out into diſgrace, or ſeverely puniſht; <hi>Ceſſantium inertiam notant, caſtigant mox, &amp; puntunt morte.</hi> They take notice of, and cenſure ſometimes with death the idleneſſe of unuſefull Drones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Now what is all the meanes of the Church, but like the Honey which <hi>Sampſon</hi> found in the carkaſſe of the dead Lyon having beene bequeathed by Kings and Potentates at their deaths, or by ſome others (who perhaps have got them by rapine or extortion from others) dedicated to pious uſes, the benefit of others, and others ſoules. And what is an idle Prieſt who never preacheth a man (as the Pſalme ſaith) in whoſe mouth there are no reproofes; a Drone without a ſting (as <hi>Heſiod</hi> well compares idle perſons) to ſtingleſſe Robbers, who did idely devoure the labours of the more induſtrious Bees: this <hi>ignavum pecus,</hi> theſe idle Drones ought not to be tolerated in the Church, but ſhould be caſt out and excommunicated. There is an old Canon of the Apoſtles to that purpoſe, I feare it is razed out of our latter Editions, but <hi>Franciſcus Torrenſis,</hi> a credible Author, ſaith, that he found it <hi>in vetuſtiſſimo libro</hi> in an old Manuſcript, If any that are Paſtors do not abide with their owne flockes, there to inſtruct them, let them be cut off from the communion of Saints; if any doe ſo little love the Lord Jeſus, as not to feed his ſheepe, let him be <hi>Anathema Maranatha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to heare how declamatory many men are in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes for the maintenance of the Clergy, and that tythes are <hi>de jure divino,</hi> is the firſt Text proſecuted with that paſſion and vehemency of Rhetoricke, as if <hi>Arius</hi> were alive againe, or the Divinity of Chriſt once more called into queſtion: But that <hi>Reſidency</hi> and Preaching at their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivings is of the like neceſſity, is contradicted by many, and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by moſt: In the one are many proviſoes, exemptions, diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and excuſes allowed, but none admitted: for the non-payment of the other a neceſſity is laid upon the poore people, and woe be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them if they pay not their tythes. Miſtake me not, I doe not goe
<pb facs="tcp:155930:11"/>about to ſlacken their forwardneſſe, or to manacle their withered hand, too many are over forward to rob the Church, and there would bee more if they could but make benefit or advantage of any <hi>Statute,</hi> if, they had any Law to plead for it, their conſciences would bee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to detaine and ſequeſter their tythes.</p>
            <p>But I ſay to Miniſters, as the Prophet to negligent Prieſts of his time, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Now therefore I pray you beſeech God that he would be gracious unto us, this hath beene by your meanes.</hi> It is the Miniſters idleneſſe ignorance, and covetouſneſſe, that hath ſo withered the han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the Laity: men are of the ſame mould they were of in old time, and perhaps not ſo comparatively wicked, neither as thoſe who cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Lord of life; yet they at the Apoſtles preaching parted with their demeanes, ſold their poſſeſſions, rather then their poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, much leſſe then the Apoſtles ſhould want. Who more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted then our Forefathers were? looking upon the decayes and ruines of Churches, Abbeyes, and Monaſteries. I cannot chooſe but fiſh out that of the Philoſopher, <hi>Veſtigia hominum video,</hi> or rather the hand of God, for it was the lazineſſe and luxury of the Church that <hi>mortmaimed</hi> their liberties.</p>
            <p>In many deeds of Feoffement in Fee there was commonly a clauſe added (ſaith <hi>Bracton, lib</hi> 1 <hi>fol.</hi> 14.) <hi>Quod licitum ſit donatorio rem da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam dare vel vendere cui voluerit, exceptis viris religioſis, &amp; Judaeis.</hi> Land was given and bequeathed with this condition that the party might give or ſell it to whom he would, unleſſe it were to Jewes and Cle gimen. A ſtrange combination in that Climactericall alteration of the Church, when Kings and Princes, the nurſing Fathers of it did not onely weane it, but ſaw it neceſſary to let it bloud, for the dropſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuperfluity of humours which domineered in the body of it. It is apparant that the idleneſſe and <hi>Non-reſidency</hi> of the Prieſts was that which improptiated all our livings. For in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Poole</hi> conventing a Synod of the Clergy in London for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church (as he called it) beginns the third Decree with theſe words, Seeing that judgement ought to beginne with the houſe of God, and reformation among the Clergy, but among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves is eſpied a notorious and ſcandalous abuſe, that thoſe who have the greateſt Livings doe not reſide upon them, but put off the cure and charge to a ſort of mercenary Hirelings, <hi>quae res omnium faeces malorum in Eccleſt a cauſam at rulit,</hi> which thing hath beene the onely cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:155930:11"/>theſe calamities, and of the Church of late: therefore be it enacted, &amp;c. And to looke a little abroad, eſpecially on that kingdome, the heroicall atchievements of which the eyes of all men now ad yes are fixt upon unto admiration, and after ages will reade with unbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>efe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guſtavus</hi> King of Sweden, Grandfather to that great avenger of bloud in our dayes, having by the expoſing of his perſon to many dangers, freed his Country from the Daniſh yoake and tyrannous u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation, did likewiſe to provide for the future quiet of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and utterly to defeat the more dangerous factions of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Trayrors, ſummon a Parliament at <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalia, Anno Dom.</hi> 1327. March 18. where among other things he did demand, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, Lands, and immoderate riches of Biſhops and other Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which was rather the maintenance of fuell, pride, luxury, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in his predeceſſors times, might be reduced to a competent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, and the reſt transferred into the Kings Exchequer, for the uſe and defrayment of the publique.</p>
            <p>This part of the Reformation the Biſhops and Prelates did moſt earneſtly labour againſt, affirming that the annuities, priviledges and endowments of the Church granted by the free donation of Kings and Emperours and confirmed by their Seales and Charrers, could not, neither ought to be revoked and diſclaimed, without incurring the great curſe and irrevocable ſentence of Excommunication and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of eternall damnation. Here was a judgement preached, but too late, for to this the Advocates of the King replyed, that true it was indeed, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel, thoſe that labour in the Word and Doctrine were worthy of double honour, a due reſpect, and ſufficient maintenance, but as for thoſe Locuſts and Catepillers, thoſe <hi>frages conſumere nati,</hi> thoſe Caterers for wormes, thoſe flow bellies, (as <hi>Epimenides</hi> calls the Cretians) who were neither ſerviceable to God nor man, ſuch ought not to be maintained of the expence of the Commonwealth; for though his predeceſſors had zealouſly perhaps, but inconſiderately, weakned the kingdome, by conferring ſo much upon them, who ſo ill imployed it, his Majeſty as he was then Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God too, and bore not the ſword in vaine, was bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to cut them ſhort, and to redreſſe ſuch diſorders.</p>
            <p>When the Prelate, were demanded what title of Scripture they had to ſhew that Biſhops ſhould intermeddle with ſecular authority, and where did God in all his Will and Teſtament give to idle loyterers
<pb facs="tcp:155930:12"/>ſuch a claime of great allowance. Alas all their skill was in the Canons, Cretals and Extravagancies, and ſo being deſtitute of other arguments, it was concluded that the priviledges and liberties of the Church were in the Kings power, and that he as the times and meanes varied, might augment or diminiſh the revenues of it.</p>
            <p>Vpon the execution of which Decree, great ſtirres and commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were made, and many buls were ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ed againſt the King by the malecontents among the Clergy, but this being Gods hand, he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Man of his right hand, for he lived religiouſly, reigned victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and died peaceably. And for ought that I can heare the <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius haeres,</hi> the third heire (God be thanked) thrives well enough, and the kingdome being ſinewed and fleſht with the addition of ſo much new ſtrength and force, flouriſheth.</p>
            <p>Had it not been pitty that that nouriſhment which is nouriſhment and releefe of ſo many diſtreſſed Chriſtians, of the recovering of ſo much ground from the encroaching of Antichriſt of propagating the Goſpel of Chriſt into many Countries heretofore captivated with a willing unbeleefe, ſhould have beene ſpent and bezied in the high fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and ſurfetted entertainments of Abbeyes and Monaſteries? Had it not beene pity that all that ſhould have beene beſtowed on Mitre or Croſier ſtaffe, which will now buy ſo many Speares and Helmets, better a great deale in my opinion beſtowed on thoſe men, who (as it was ſayd of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi>) have hazarded their lives for the name of the Lord Jeſus; then thoſe who could not ſpeake a good word for him? All you therefore that wiſh the good of the Church, and would ſee Jeruſalem in proſperity all your life long if you would heap coales of fire upon your enemies heads, and make the ſinne of Impropriation Sacriledge, be diligent in the Lords worke, and then you need not be ſo loud in calling for your wages; for the hire of the labourer which is kept backe by fraud, cryeth (ſaith Saint <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 3.4.) and the cry thereof ſhall enter into the eares of the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
            <p>The beſt way then not onely to procure the maintenance, but to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the welfare and proſperity of the Commonwealth, is to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in preaching.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> a Courtier, one that was neere to the King (as it was thought) both in perſon and alliance, teacheth us this Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call policy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.67.78. <hi>Ye that make mention of the Lord, or ye that are the Lords Remembrancers, keepe no filence till he make Jeruſalem a
<pb facs="tcp:155930:12"/>praiſe on the earth. The Lord hath ſworne by his right hand, and by the arme of his ſtrength.</hi> (it is the hand and arme in which are the hearts of Kings, much more of the common people) <hi>ſurely I will no more give thy corne to be meat for thine enemies, and the ſonnes of the ſtrangers ſhall not drinke thy wines for the which thou haſt laboured, but they that have gathered it, and they that have brought it together ſhall eate it in the Courts of my Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
